Translators' Note
What shall we talk about?
What do you think is the most important thing
that we three can talk about?
Well, the one thing... I've had an idea lately,
and there's one thing that's been on my mind,
and I've been getting it from when we talked before,
and that is there's a feeling you've been conveying
that life comes first and not thought or work.
Something like that. In other
words, that I find in myself,
and I find I think that most
people are caught up in the fact that...
You know, you said once,
we live second-hand lives.
If we could talk about that, I think,
the second-handness of our life.
What do you mean?
Well, in relation to that,
I perhaps would like to
talk about the question of wholeness.
Yes, of wholeness.
Shall we talk about that first?
Which first?
And then include yours.
Sure. I mean, I think this is part of it.
I see that the second-handness is not wholeness.
I wonder how we can approach this question.
Knowing that most people are fragmented, broken up,
and not whole,
how do we tackle or approach this question?
Through direct awareness of the fragmentation.
No, I would like to... I'm just asking because...
Are we discussing it theoretically?
No.
Verbally?
Or taking ourselves, you, we three,
taking ourselves as we are,
and examining what we mean by fragmented?
Right.
And then work from there what is the whole,
not theoretically or verbally.
Right.
Then I think that has vitality, that has some meaning.
Right, right.
Well, if we see the fragmentation, the wholeness is there.
No, no.
Or will it be there?
Don't assume anything.
Oh, that's right.
That's too fast.
Then we are off to theory.
Okay. Right, right.
You know, we've been talking,
there are a lot of students here, this question.
Dr Bohm was there too.
And whether we can ever
be aware of ourselves at all.
Or we are only aware of patches,
not the totality of fragmentations.
I don't know if I am conveying this.
Well, you can. Go ahead.
Yes.
Can one be aware, conscious, know,
the various fragments?
Or examining one by one by one by one,
and who is the examiner?
Is he also a fragment,
who has assumed an authority?
So when we talk about being aware of fragments,
socially, morally, ethically, religiously, business, art,
you know, the whole activity is fragmented.
Is one aware of fragments?
Is one aware of the movement of these fragments?
Yes.
Or do you take one fragment and examine it?
Or say, yes, I am aware of that,
and not the many.
You follow what I am saying?
I am following you.
I think you are mostly aware of...
I seem to...
When I think of what you are saying,
I seem to be aware
of a kind of many fragments.
Are you?
Well, not one at a time, you know,
spread it like that, like a machine gun.
Yes. So you are really aware one by one.
Right.
And caught up by the movement of the fragments.
One by one. Is that so?
Are you sure that it is so?
Yes. I think, I mean, it seems to be that...
Well, then sometimes you can take a step back,
or you seem to take a step back,
or I seem to take a step back,
and I am aware of these many.
No, when Dr. Worm asked,
can't we talk over together
this question of wholeness,
which implies holiness, health, sanity, and all that,
I wonder from what source he is asking that question.
Yes. You mean, is he coming from a fragmented position,
or is he coming from a whole position?
No, no, if he is asking from the whole position,
there is no question.
So I would like to, if one may ask,
are we aware of the fragments as a whole,
a collection of fragments,
or are we aware of one fragment at each time?
What do you say, sir?
Well, in general, the thing presents itself first
as primarily one fragment...
One fragment at a time.
...with a background of all the other fragments,
perhaps dimly present.
I mean, in the beginning,
that one fragment seems to take emphasis
or preeminence in awareness.
Doesn't that one fragment fragment out quickly
into many little fragments?
I have an idea,
and then that idea is in contrast to another idea,
so I'm immediately caught up into two fragments there.
And then I have another idea,
which is the repetition of that first idea,
so I'm caught up in a movement of fragments,
rather than...
I mean, my attitude is fragmented,
my relationship is fragmented,
my very substance of movement
is a feeling of fragmentation.
I don't have any center when I'm fragmented.
I'm not...
I'm not sure about that.
That's a question.
I'm not at all sure...
No, no.
...that there is no center when you're fragmented.
Well, I think definitely there is a center.
There is.
I mean, that is the major fragment you're aware of.
The major fragment, that's right.
I mean, that...
Then let's go into that more.
Well, I just think that there is a center
which you may sense anywhere,
say here or here.
Yeah.
And that seems to be the center of everything, right?
Everything that's connected to everything, right?
Well, I see what you're saying,
but I feel that when the fragmentation is going on,
it's like the center is looking for
itself.
It feels like it's not a center.
Are you aware of the fragmentation?
Not fragmentation is going on.
No, you're not.
I'm not.
Then what are we aware of?
I think that's a terrific question,
because I think when there's fragmentation,
what we're aware of is like being sucked forward
into more fragments.
In other words, there's a kind of movement
of more fragmentation, more fragmentation,
more fragmentation, which is what we're aware of.
It's what you've talked about in terms of pleasure.
It's like pleasure is pulling us forward
into more fragments.
This would give me pleasure.
That would give me pleasure.
And it's that feeling of pieces.
Before we go into the question of pleasure,
are we aware actually from a center
which says, I am fragmented?
That is the question, isn't it?
Right, that's the question.
Well, we're both aware of a center
and from a center, you say.
That's it.
And this center seems to be, as you say,
the fragment that is dominating
or attempting to dominate.
That center is the dominating factor.
Yes.
Which is in itself a fragment.
Yes, I mean, this center is itself...
Well, it seems to be the center of your being,
as it were, the center
of the ego or the self,
which one might think is the whole.
Quite, quite.
Because it's in contact with everything, you see.
In other words...
Would you say having a center
is the very cause of fragmentation?
Yes, I would say that, although at first sight
it seems quite different to me.
At first sight it seems...
And I think that's important,
the difference between it.
At first sight it doesn't seem that way.
Well, at first sight it seems that the center
is what is organizing everything into a whole.
Right.
Yes.
In other words, one feels one wants a center
to bring everything to a whole,
to stop the fragmentation.
Yes, try to bring about integration,
try to...
Wholeness, yes.
Wholeness and all that.
Right, if you feel the fragmentation
and then you center here and you say,
I can see all the fragmentations,
but that's still center.
No, but I'm asking whether
when there is a center,
doesn't it make for fragments?
That I see.
I see what you're saying,
but I'm trying to take it from the...
What is the experience when there is fragmentation?
There doesn't seem to be a center.
A contradiction.
Right.
But it doesn't feel like a center.
No, contradiction.
So when there are fragments,
I am aware of the fragments
because of contradiction.
Because of...
Because opposing factors.
You mean by contradiction also conflict.
Conflict, yes.
Out of contradiction there is conflict.
Then I'm aware that there are fragments.
I'm working in an area of fragments.
Right.
But then, yes,
and then I'm not aware of the fact
that I have in fact got a center.
That's the self-deception right there.
No, I think, don't you think,
if I may suggest,
that where there is conflict,
then only you are aware
で
aware of a conflict, of contradiction.
That is, one is aware only when there is conflict.
Right?
And then the next awareness, the next movement is...
conflict arises out of conflict,
conflict arises out of fragmentation,
opposing elements, opposing desires,
opposing wishes, opposing thoughts.
But are you saying that these
oppose first before one is aware,
and then suddenly you are aware through the unpleasantness
or the pain of the
opposition, that the conflict is unpleasant?
Yes, conflict is unpleasant and
therefore one is aware that...
That something is wrong. Wrong. Yes.
Yes, or something is wrong,
not just simply wrong, but wrong with the whole thing.
Whole thing, of course.
Sir, after all, self-consciousness,
when you are aware of
yourself only when there is pain,
or intense pleasure.
Otherwise you are not aware of yourself.
Right.
So fragmentation with its conflict
brings this sense of, I
am aware, I am in conflict.
Otherwise there is no awareness.
I wonder if I am...
Yes, go ahead.
You are saying that the very fragmentation itself
breeds the centre.
Breeds the centre.
And the centre has bred the
fragmentation, so it is like a...
Yes, back and forth.
Right.
Well, I mean, would you
say that the thought in itself
before there is a centre breeds conflict?
Yes, I mean...
Thought...
Or is there a thought before a centre?
Is there... Oh, thought before the centre.
Yes.
I mean, one view is to
say that the centre and thought
are always co-existent and one breeds the other.
One breeds the other, quite right.
Or the other view is to
say that there might be thought first
and that produces conflict and then that produces a centre.
No, let's go into that a little bit.
That's a good one, huh?
Does thought exist before conflict?
Before a centre.
Before the centre.
Which centre only...
One is aware of the
centre only when there is conflict.
Yes, because that comes in apparently
to try to bring about wholeness again.
You see, to take charge of everything.
The centre tries to take
charge or try to create wholeness.
Yes, to bring all the factors together.
But centre itself is a fragment.
Yes, but it doesn't know that.
Of course, it doesn't know, but it
thinks it can bring all the fragments together,
make it a whole.
So Dr. Bohm is asking a question which is,
did thought exist before the centre
or the centre existed before the thought?
Or the two together.
Right, right.
Or he's also asking, does thought create the centre?
Thought creates the centre.
That would be the action, the very creation
in the...
I mean, sort of an after effect of the thought.
In other words, is the organism...
is the production of thought
the very cause of a centre?
That I think carries it...
Are you asking...
Yes, let's be clear on this point too.
Are we asking, did thought create the centre?
Yes, and there was therefore a
kind of thought before a centre.
Yes, thought before the centre. That's it.
Which came into contradiction.
Yes. Thought created...
Did the thought create the centre
or the centre existed before the thought?
Right.
Or else the centre was...
That's a view which is common.
I mean, people think the
centre is me who was first.
Me is the first.
Then I began to think, right?
Yes.
Or...
No, I think thought exists before the centre.
Yes.
Then we have to ask the question,
and I don't know if we want
to get into it at this minute,
but then we have to ask the question of
why is there thought?
Or what is thought?
Oh, that's a different matter.
Right.
Do we go into that?
That might be a long story.
That's a long story.
I don't think that's for now.
Yes.
But we have to get at that.
No, but as we start...
Let's stay with what we started with.
Yes.
We started out asking,
can we talk about the wholeness of life?
Right.
How can one be aware of that wholeness?
If one is fragmented?
That's the next question.
Well...
You can't be aware of the whole
if I'm only looking through a small hole.
Right, right.
Huh?
Right.
But on the other hand,
in actuality, you are the whole.
Ah!
That is a theory.
Is it?
That's what...
A supposition, yes.
Of course it is.
When you are fragmented,
how can you assume that you are the whole?
Well, that's a wonderful...
I mean, that's an issue because...
How am I to know I'm fragmented?
That's what we are asking.
Yes.
When are you aware that you are fragmented?
Only when there is conflict.
Right.
That's right.
When there are two opposing desires,
opposing elements of movements,
then there is conflict.
And you say,
well, I'm not going to be fragmented.
Then you have pain,
or whatever it is,
and then you become conscious.
Right, right.
But at those moments,
it oftentimes happens
that you don't want to let go of the...
I mean, it's like you feel your fragmentation...
No, no, no.
That's a different matter.
Right.
What we are asking is,
can the fragment dissolve itself...
Yeah.
Okay.
...and then only it's possible to see the whole?
You cannot be fragmented and then wish for the whole.
Right.
Then it's merely...
All you really know is your fragmentation.
That's all we know.
That's right.
Therefore, let's stick to that...
Okay.
...and not beat around the bush and say,
well, let's talk about the whole
and all the rest of it.
Yes.
I mean, the supposition that there
is a whole may be apparently reasonable,
but as long as you're fragmented...
That's right.
...you could never see it.
Of course.
It would be just an assumption.
Right.
You may think you've experienced it once,
but that's also an assumption because you don't...
That's gone already.
Absolutely.
Quite right.
You know, I wonder if there's not a tremendous pain
or something that goes on
when I'm aware of my fragmentation.
I mean, that's the loneliness somehow or the other.
Look, sir, can you be aware of your fragments?
That you are an American, that I'm a Hindu,
you are a Jew, you are a...
a communist, this or...
You just live in that state.
Yes.
You don't say, well, I know I am a Hindu.
You...
It's only when you are challenged.
Mm-hmm.
It's only when you say, what are you?
Then you say, yes, I'm an
Indian or a Hindu or an Arab.
Or when the country is challenged and
you have to go to war, yes.
Yes, when the country...
Of course.
Right.
You're saying that I'm living totally reactively.
No, you're totally living in a kind of...
What?
Miasma, confusion.
From one piece to the next.
Yes.
From one reaction to the next reaction.
Reward and punishment in that movement.
Right.
So can we be aware actually now...
Mm-hmm.
Of the various fragments?
That I am a Hindu, that I am a Jew, that I am an Arab, that I am a communist, that I
am a Catholic, that I am a businessman, I am married, I have responsibilities, I am an artist, I am a scientist.
You follow?
These various sociological fragmentations.
Right.
As well as psychological fragmentations.
That's exactly what I started with.
Right.
This feeling that I am a fragment, this feeling
that that's where I get absorbed, is being a fragment.
Which you call the individual.
That I call important.
Not just the individual.
You call that important.
Right.
That I have to work.
Quite.
See, that it's significant.
So can we now, in talking over together, be
aware of the fact that we are all human beings?
Together.
Be aware that I am that.
Mm-hmm.
I am a fragment, and therefore creating more fragments, more conflict, more
misery, more confusion, more sorrow, because when there is conflict, it affects everything.
Right.
Can you be aware of
it as we are discussing it?
Mm-hmm.
I can be aware as
we are discussing it a little.
Not a little.
I don't know about that.
A little.
That's the trouble.
Why can't I be aware of it?
No, sir.
You are only aware of it when there is conflict.
It is not a conflict in you now.
Yes.
But is it possible to
be aware of it without conflict?
That's the next thing, yes.
That requires quite a different approach.
Well, how will we consider this different?
Quite a different approach.
Mm-hmm.
But I was thinking of looking at one point that the importance of these fragments is that
when I identify myself and say, I am this, I am that, I mean the whole of me.
In other words, I am the whole of
me is rich or poor or American or whatever.
Yes.
And therefore it's all important because it's the whole.
See, I think it seems that the trouble
is that the fragment claims that it's the whole.
Quite right.
It makes itself very important.
Right.
Mm-hmm.
It takes up the whole life.
Yeah.
This is life.
Then comes a contradiction and then
comes another fragment saying it's the whole.
Look what is happening in Northern Ireland.
Mm-hmm.
The Arab world, the Mideast world, the Muslim and the
Hindu, you know, this whole world is broken up that way.
Mm-hmm.
Outside and inside.
Me and you.
Yes, me and you, we and
they and all the rest of it.
Right.
But I mean, that's the difference between
saying we have a lot of different objects
in the room, you know, which are
separate and so on, which we can handle.
That's a different thing.
There's no problem there.
But if we say I am this, I'm wholly this,
then I also say I'm wholly that and I'm wholly
that.
Well, that you're bringing
in something different here, though.
That is exactly how it is that
we come to believe in these fragments.
Because we look at objects and we say
they're separate things before I'm a separate thing.
I question that, sir.
Right.
Say, for instance, the Arab and the Israeli.
Are they aware that I am an Arab, I
want to fight that somebody else who is not?
Or I have an idea, you follow?
Idea.
What do you mean?
An idea that I'm an Arab?
Yes.
But the idea is that that's very important
as well, that I am totally an Arab.
Yes, I'm totally an Arab.
It's all important.
Yes.
That's the form of the idea, isn't it?
And now if somebody else has the idea
I'm a Jew, that's all important, therefore they
must destroy each other.
Impossible to do it.
Quite.
And I think the politicians, the
religious people are encouraging all this.
But they also are running the business.
They're not running it by fragments.
Because they are fragmented themselves.
See, that's the whole point.
People who are in power,
being fragmented, sustain the fragmentations.
Right.
Well, it's the only way to
get into power is to be fragmented.
Of course.
Yes, well, he says it's all important that
I should be a politician and successful and
so on.
Of course.
But I mean...
This movement...
Into fragmentation almost...
It seems to be caused by something.
It seems to be...
Now, if you ask...
Is this what you're asking?
What is the cause of this fragmentation?
Yes.
Right?
Right.
What is the cause of the fragmentation?
What breeds it?
What sucks us into it?
What brings about fragmentation?
Yes.
Well, you know, what breeds it?
What brings it about?
When the mother and child start...
When the child separates from the mother, right?
Biologically.
No, psychologically.
Biologically, yes.
The child starts able to walk.
And the child can walk
away, and then he runs back.
And then he runs back and he looks back.
He says, is she still there?
And gradually...
Gradually moves away.
Now, the mother that is not able to let go...
Hey, come back here!
Right.
And scares the child to death because the child thinks,
I can't do it.
If she says I can't
do it, I can't do it.
Right.
But, no, we are asking something very important,
which is, what is the cause of this fragmentation?
Yes.
That's why I was getting into that.
There's some cause there.
I mean, it begins there.
I've got to hold on to something.
No, no.
Just look at it, sir.
What has brought fragmentation in you?
Well, my immediate response is the
need to hold on to something.
No, no.
Much deeper than that.
Much more.
Look at it.
Let's go slowly at it.
Not immediate responses.
What brings this conflict?
This conflict...
This conflict which indicates I'm fragmented,
and then I ask the question, what brings this fragmentation?
Fragmentation.
Right.
What is the cause of it?
Are you saying there's a conflict
and there something happens that
causes fragmentation in the conflict?
No.
Is that what you're saying?
You're saying fragmentation causes it.
Is the cause of the conflict.
Now, then what is the cause of the fragmentation?
That's right.
All right.
So that's important.
Why are you and I and
the majority of the world fragmented?
What is the source of it?
It seems we won't find the cause by
going back in time to a certain happening.
No, I'm not looking for genetics.
I'm looking for right this second.
What I was...
I come upon a...
To put it in this way,
to put it in these words,
it seems to do that.
There's a focusing or a holding
on to something inside my movement.
Sir, leave...
Look at it as though you're...
Not from Dr. Shainberg's point of view,
just look at it.
Put it on the table and
look at it objectively as it was.
What brings about this fragmentation?
Fear.
No, no.
No, I'm not...
No, much more.
Maybe the fragmentation causes fear.
Yes, that's it.
That's it.
Why am I a Hindu?
I'm not a Hindu.
I'm not an Indian.
I have no nationality.
But suppose I have...
I call myself a Hindu.
What makes me a Hindu?
Well...
What...
Conditioning makes you would make you a Hindu?
Which is...
What is the background, what is the feeling or
what is this that makes me say I'm a Hindu?
Which is a fragmentation, obviously.
Right, right.
What makes it?
My father, my grandfather, my generations of generations after
10,000 or 5,000 years said you are a Brahmin.
Right.
And I say, all right, I'm a Brahmin.
I'm a Brahmin.
You don't say, all right, I'm a Brahmin.
You say, I am a Brahmin.
No, you say, I am a Brahmin.
Right.
That's quite different.
You say, I am a Brahmin because it's like you...
Yes.
They work on you that way.
I'm a Brahmin.
Like you're saying, I'm a Christian.
Right.
Which is what?
That is...
Tradition.
Tradition, conditioning, sociology, history, culture...
Climate.
Climate, everything.
Everything.
Behind that, what is that?
Behind that is man's...
No, no, don't theorize.
Look at it in yourself.
Well, that gives me a place, an identity, a...
I know who I am then.
I have my little niche.
Who made that niche?
Well, I made it and they helped me make it.
In other words, I'm cooperating in this very...
No, no, you are not cooperating.
You are it.
I am it, right.
But I mean, that's right.
There's a whole thing is moving
toward putting me in a hole.
So what made you, the
great, great, great, arriere, grandparents, made...
created this environment, this culture, this
whole structure of human existence with all
its misery and all the messes?
What has brought it about?
Which is the fragmentation, with
all the conflict and all the...
The same action then as now.
Now.
That's all I'm asking.
Yes.
The same action that made that is now, right now.
Exactly.
The Babylonians, the Egyptians, the...
Is now.
We are exactly the same monkeys now.
Now, now, right.
Well, this was my...
This is what I was getting at at the beginning.
This is all gives me my secondhand existence.
Yes.
Proceed.
Let's go into it.
Let's find out what...
Why man has bred or brought about this state.
And which we accept.
You follow?
Gladly and or unwillingly.
Love it.
I'm willing to kill somebody...
Right.
...because he's a communist or a socialist.
Or a socialist, socially, or whatever it is.
Exactly what is going on in
Northern Ireland, in the Middle East.
Well, everywhere.
I mean, you know, doctors, lawyers...
Of course, of course.
It's the same problem.
Same problem.
I have...
My sense of it is that I...
It stops me.
It keeps...
It closes me off.
It keeps me...
It keeps the movement...
You know, it's like the tree doesn't get in.
If I know who I am,
then I don't look at the tree.
Yes, sir.
But you're not...
We're not...
You're not...
You're not answering my question.
I have some answers, but I...
Is it the desire for security?
Biological as well as psychological security?
You could say yes.
If I belong to something,
to some organization, to some group,
to some sect, to some
ideological community, I am safe there.
Right.
Well, it's not clear because you may feel safe.
I feel safe there, but it may not be safety.
Yes, but why don't I see
that I'm not really safe, you see?
Because I'm so...
What?
You can...
It's coming.
You go into it.
I don't see it.
No.
You just look.
I join a community.
Right.
I'm a doctor.
Yes.
You're a doctor.
And I've got all these ideas.
You have a special position in society.
Right.
And I've got a lot
of ideas of how things work.
No.
You have a special position in society.
And there you are completely safe.
Safe.
Right.
You can malpractice and all the rest
of it, but you are very protected...
Right.
...by other doctors, by other organizations,
a group of doctors who are all...
You follow?
Right.
...who feel secure.
But it's essential that I shouldn't inquire
too far to feel secure, isn't it?
Yes.
I mean, in other words, I must sort
of stop my inquiry at a certain point.
I'm a doctor.
I'm finished.
I don't ask any questions about it.
That's right.
But if I started to ask questions...
Ah, then you're out.
But if people say, don't ask questions, you're out.
Yes.
If I begin to ask questions about my
community and my relationship with that community, my
relationship with the world,
my relationship with my neighbor...
I'm finished, I'm out of the community.
Right.
I'm lost.
That's right.
So, to feel safe, secure, protected, I belong.
I depend.
Right.
In a day or so,
I depend wholly, in some sense.
If I don't have that, then
I feel the whole thing is sunk.
But you see, look, this is even more...
This is good.
You see, not only do I depend.
Not only do I depend, but every problem that
I now have is with reference to this dependency.
I don't know from nothing about the patient.
I only know about how the
patient doesn't fit into my system.
Quite, quite.
So that's my conflict.
He's your victim.
That's right, my victim.
Right.
But again, you see...
He loves that.
But why...
It's still not clear why
I should go on with it.
I think that, in other words, as long
as I don't ask questions, I can feel comfortable,
and I feel uncomfortable when I do
ask questions, very deeply uncomfortable, because the whole
of my situation is challenged.
But then why...
But then if I look at it more
broadly, I see the whole thing has no foundation.
I mean, it's all dangerous.
In other words, this community itself is a
mess and may collapse, or even if the whole
of it doesn't collapse.
You see, you can't count
on the academic profession any more.
You know, they may not give money for universities.
You see?
Quite.
Everything is changing so fast that
you don't know where you are.
So why should I go on
with not asking questions, you see?
Why don't I ask questions?
Yes.
Because fear.
Fear.
But that fear is from fragmentation.
Of course.
So is it the beginning of this fragmentation?
Yes.
So fragmentation takes place when one is seeking security?
But why wouldn't it...
Both biologically as well as psychologically.
Primarily psychologically, then biologically.
Right.
Physically.
But isn't the tendency to seek
security physically built into the human organism?
Yes, that's right.
It is.
I must have food, clothes, shelter.
It is absolutely necessary.
Right.
And when that is threatened, say if
I question the communist system altogether, living in
Russia, I'm a non-person.
But let's go a little bit slower here.
Why would... you're suggesting there
that in my need for security...
Biologically, I must have some fragmentation.
No, sir.
Biologically fragmentation takes place, the
insecurity takes place, when psychologically
I want security.
Okay.
I don't know if I'm making myself clear.
Wait a minute.
That is, if I don't psychologically belong to a group...
Hmm?
Then I'm out of that group.
Hmm-hmm.
And then I'm insecure.
I'm insecure.
Hmm?
Right.
And because the group
gives me security, physical security...
Hmm-hmm.
Hmm?
They accept everything they give me, say to me.
Right.
But the moment I object psychologically to the...
Hmm-hmm.
...to the...
...to the structure of the society...
Hmm-hmm.
...or the community, I'm lost.
Right.
I mean, this is an obvious fact.
Yes.
Right.
Well, you're suggesting then that the basic
insecurity that we live in is being conditioned.
The response to this is... the
answer to this is a conditioned fragmentation.
Partly.
Yes.
And that the movement of fragmentation is the conditioning.
Sir, look.
Look.
If there was no fragmentation, both
historically, geographically, nationally, no nations, we'd
live perfectly safely.
Hmm?
We'd all be protected.
We'd all have food.
We'd all have...
You follow?
Houses.
There would be no wars.
We'd all be one.
Hmm-hmm.
He's my brother.
He's...
I am him.
He's me.
But this fragmentation prevents that taking place.
Right.
So you're even suggesting more something there.
You're suggesting that we would
be... we would help each other.
Oh, naturally.
I would help...
Obviously.
That's saying a lot.
We're sort of going around in
a circle, though, still, because you say...
No, I'm not going in a circle.
I won't get back into it.
I won't get back to something which is...
Yeah, right.
That's it.
If there were no nationalities, no ideological groups,
et cetera, and so on and so on, we'd
be perfectly...
I mean, we'd have everything we want.
Hmm.
You see, penning and armaments, all the rest of it.
Hmm-hmm.
Proper education, all that.
That is prevented because...
Hmm.
I am a Hindu, you are
an Arab, he is a Russian.
You follow?
All that is prevented, and we are
asking, why does this fragmentation take place?
What is the source of it?
Is it knowledge?
Hmm.
Yes, sir.
It is knowledge, you think.
You say, yes, sir.
Is it knowledge?
I'm sure it is, but
I'm putting it as a question.
Yeah.
It certainly seems to be...
No, no.
Look into it.
Let's find out.
What do you mean by knowledge?
What are you talking about there?
The word to know, huh?
Do I know you?
Or I have known you?
Hmm-hmm.
I can never say I know you.
Literally, I mean actually, it would be
an abomination to say I know you.
Right.
Hmm-hmm.
I have known you.
Because you, in the meantime,
are changing, you have all your...
You follow?
There is a great deal
of movement going on in you.
Right.
And to say I know you means I am
acquainted or intimate with that movement which is all
going on in you.
There'd be an impudence on my
part to say I know you.
Right.
That's right.
Because not only that, that would be denying
your effect on me, which is causing me...
Which is a change from
knowing you, from being with you.
So knowing, to know is the path.
Huh?
Would you say to that?
Yes.
I mean, what we know is the past and...
Knowledge is the past.
But I mean, the danger is
that we call it the present.
I mean, is that...
See, the danger is that we call knowledge the present.
That's just it.
In other words, if we said the past is
the past, then wouldn't you say it needn't fragment?
What's that?
If we said, if we recognized or we acknowledged
that the past is the past, it's gone, and
therefore what we know is past...
Past, yes.
Then that would not introduce fragmentation.
That would...
Quite right.
But if we say what we know is
what is present now, then we are introducing fragmentation.
Quite right, quite.
Because we are imposing this partial knowledge on the whole.
So would you say knowledge is
one of the factors of fragmentation?
Sir, that's saying an awful...
You follow?
It's a large pill to swallow.
But also, you're implying there are other factors.
Yes.
But...
And that may be the only factor.
Yes.
But, you see, I think we should look at
it this way, that people have hoped through knowledge
to overcome fragmentation...
Of course.
...to produce a system of knowledge
that will put it all together.
Again, Bronowski's ascent of man
through knowledge, emphasizing knowledge, knowledge,
knowledge.
Is that not one of the major
factors, or perhaps the factor of fragmentation?
My experience tells me I'm a Hindu.
My experience tells me I know what God is.
Well, wouldn't we better say that confusion
about the role of knowledge is what's the
cause of fragmentation?
Yes.
In other words, knowledge itself.
See, if you say knowledge is always the cause...
No.
...then I said we began by asking...
Yes, I mean, let's make it clear.
...yes, of course, of course.
So that's what we said yesterday in our talk.
Art is putting things in its right place.
So I'm putting knowledge in its right place.
Right.
Yes, so we're not confused about it anymore.
Of course.
Right.
You know, I was just going
to bring in this rather interesting example.
A patient of mine was teaching me something the
other day, and she said, I have the feeling
that as a doctor, the way you operate is...
She says, there's a group of doctors who've
seen certain kinds of patients, and if they
do X to them, they'll get certain
kind of effects, and they achieve things.
She says, you're not talking to me.
You're doing this to me, hoping you'll get this result.
Quite.
That's what you're saying.
No, a little more so than that.
We are saying, both Dr. Bohm and
I, we are saying knowledge has its place.
Right.
Now let's go into that.
Like driving a car, learning a language, and so on.
Yes, we could say, why is that not fragmentation?
We could make it clear.
You see that, in other words, if we
drive a car using knowledge, that is not fragmentation.
No.
But when knowledge is used psychologically...
Yes, but I mean, one should
see more clearly what the difference is.
You see, that is the car itself, as I
see it, is a part, a limited part, and therefore
it can be handled by knowledge.
You mean it's a limited part of life.
Of life, yes.
Right.
And so and so.
I mean the whole of me, you see.
That's right.
And therefore I'm applying a part to the whole.
I'm trying to cover the whole by a part.
When knowledge assumes it understands
the whole, then begins the mystery.
But it's often very tricky, because I'm
not explicitly spelling out that I understand
the whole, but it's implicit by saying, everything
is this way, or I am this way.
Quite, quite.
But it implies that the
whole is this way, you see.
The whole of me, the whole
of life, the whole of the world.
Yes.
Well, what Krishnaji was saying.
I mean, like, I know you.
That's how we do with ourselves.
We say, I know this about me, rather than
being open to the new event, or even being
aware of the fragmentation.
Yes.
When I'm saying about you, then I shouldn't
say I know all, because you're not a limited
part like a machine.
You see, that's what's implied.
You see, the machine is fairly limited, and
we can know all that's relevant about it,
or almost all anyway.
Sometimes it breaks down.
Quite, quite.
But when it comes to another person,
that's immensely beyond what you could really know.
I mean, that's… the past
experience doesn't tell you the essence.
Are you saying, Dr. Bob, that when
knowledge spills over into the psychological field…
Well, also in another field, which
I call the whole in general.
You see, sometimes it spills over into
the philosophical field when man tries to make
a metaphysical view of the whole universe.
Of course.
That's, of course.
I mean, that's purely theoretical, and
that has no meaning to me personally.
But I mean, that's one of the
ways in which it does that, you see.
Yes.
It goes wrong.
I mean, see, some people feel that when
they are discussing metaphysics of the whole universe,
it is not psychological.
It probably is, but the motives behind it are psychological.
But some people may feel that they are
making a theory of the universe, not discussing psychology.
I mean, I think it's a matter of getting…
The language.
The language, quite.
Well, I mean, you see this with what
you're saying, or what he's saying, can be extended
to the way people are.
They have a metaphysics about other people.
I know all other people are not to be trusted.
Quite.
Or you have a metaphysics about yourself,
saying, I am such and such a person.
Right.
And I have a metaphysics that life
is hopeless and I must depend on these…
No.
All that I can say is…
we can say is, we are fragmented.
That's a fact.
Right.
And I am aware of those fragmented minds.
There is an awareness of
the fragmented mind because of conflict.
Right.
That's right.
You were saying before we have got to
have an approach where we're not aware just because
of that.
Yes.
Right?
That's right.
Are we coming to that?
Coming?
Yes.
So from there, conflict, I say,
what is the source of this conflict?
Mm-hmm.
Source is fragmentation, obviously.
Now what brings about fragmentation?
What is the cause of this, behind it?
We said perhaps knowledge.
Perhaps knowledge.
Knowledge, psychologically I use knowledge.
I know myself.
I really don't know because I'm changing, moving.
Mm-hmm.
Or I use knowledge for my own satisfaction.
Wow.
For my position, for my success, for
becoming a great man in the world.
I am a great scholar.
I have read a million books and
I can tell you all about it.
It gives me a position, a prestige, a status.
Mm-hmm.
So is that it?
That fragmentation takes place when there
is a desire for security, psychological security,
which prevents biological security.
Mm-hmm.
Right.
You see, right.
And therefore security may be one of the factors.
Security in knowledge.
Right.
Used wrongly.
Well, could you say now that some sort of
mistake has been made that, say, a man feels
insecure biologically and he thinks, you know, what
shall I do, and he makes a mistake in
the sense that he tries
to obtain psychological sense of security?
Yes.
By thinking, you know, by knowledge.
By knowledge, yes.
That's…
By knowing.
Yeah.
By repeating himself.
By depending on all of these structures.
One feels secure in having an ideal.
Right.
Huh?
That's so true.
But you see, but somewhere, I say, I
always ask why a person makes this mistake.
You see, in other words, if thought had
been… or if the mind had been absolutely clear,
let's say, it would never have done that.
Isn't that right?
Well, that's if the mind had been absolutely
clear, but we just said that there's biological
insecurity.
That's…
That's a fact.
But that doesn't imply that you have to delude yourself.
Quite a bit.
But that implies that the organism… no,
it doesn't… that's right, but it implies
that that has to be met.
Yeah, but the delusion doesn't meet it.
Right.
But that's the nub of the issue.
Go on further.
You can see more.
I mean, there's that biological fact
of my constant uncertainty, the biological
fact of constant change.
That is created through psychological fragmentation.
My biological uncertainty?
Of course.
I may lose my job.
I may have no money tomorrow.
Now, let's look at that, to
say, I may have no money tomorrow.
Now, you say that may be an actual fact.
Now, but the question is, what happens?
You see, what would you say if the
man were clear, what would be his response?
I…
He would never be put in that position.
I mean, he wouldn't get there in the first place.
He wouldn't have that question.
But I mean, suppose he
finds himself without money, you see.
He'll do something.
He won't… his mind won't just go…
Yeah, go out in a nightmare.
He won't have to have all the
money he thinks he has to have.
But aside from that, he
won't go into this wild confusion.
No, absolutely.
I mean, the problem, 99 percent of the time,
I certainly agree, is that we all think we
need more, that we have this
ideal of what we should have.
No.
And we are trying to stick to one point,
which is, what is the cause of this fragmentation?
Right.
We said knowledge spilling over into
the field where it should not enter.
Yeah, but why does it do so, you say?
Why does it do it?
It's fairly simple.
Why?
No, please.
We get there.
We've got another five, six minutes more.
Yeah.
It's fairly simple.
All of that.
I think it's a very important thing.
Well, my sense of it is, from what we've
been saying, is that it does it in a delusion
of security.
It thinks that there is — thought
creates the illusion that there is security there.
Yes, but why doesn't intelligence show
that there's no security, you see?
I mean, you see, I'm not —
Why doesn't intelligence show that there's no security?
Yeah.
In other words, I —
Can fragmented mind be intelligent?
No.
Well, it resists intelligence.
It resists intelligence.
It can pretend to be intelligent.
Yes.
Well, are you saying that once
the mind fragments, then intelligence is gone?
Yeah.
But now that — hm?
You said, yeah.
Yeah.
I mean, let's —
Yes, but now you're creating a
serious problem, because you're also saying that,
you know, there can be an end to fragmentation.
That's right.
You see, at first sight
there seemed to be a contradiction.
Is that clear?
It looks like that, but it's not.
I —
All I know is fragmentation.
Therefore —
That's what I've got.
— let's stick to it.
Right.
And see if it can end up.
We'll go through it.
I am —
But you say, if you say the fragmented
mind, you know, it cannot — intelligence cannot
operate there.
No.
I feel like one answer to your question
is, is that, you know, we've talked about it
in terms of conditioning.
I feel like I'm a victim
or I'm caught by this offering.
You offer me —
Right.
You tell me, look, old boy,
I think that this can help you.
Here's a fragment.
Come along.
And I feel like thought does that.
You know, come.
My mother or my father says,
look, it's good to be a doctor.
Or this one says it's
good to go to do this.
Yes.
And, sir, is psychological security
more important than biological security?
Well, one of — you know, that's an interesting question.
Well, I —
We've got five minutes.
Come to it.
Well, no.
One thing, we are convinced somehow
that I think the society —
No, I'm asking — don't move away from the question.
I'm asking, is psychological security much
more important than biological — physical
security, biological security?
It isn't, but it feels like it is.
No, no, no.
Don't move away from it.
I'm asking you to stick to it.
To you.
Are you asking, what is the fact?
What is the —
What's the fact?
Yes.
I would say yes.
Why?
It's psychological security.
It seems —
Not —
What is actually true, isn't it?
Actually true, no.
Biological security is more important.
Biological.
Are you sure?
No, no, I'd turn it around.
I think psychological security is
what actually I worry about most.
Psychological security.
Right.
That's what I worry about most.
Which prevents biological security.
Right.
I forget about biological security.
No.
Because I'm seeking psychological security in
ideas, in knowledge, in pictures, in images,
in conclusions, all the rest of it,
which prevents me from having biological, physical
security for me, for my sons,
for my children, for my brothers.
I can't have it.
Because psychological security says I'm a Hindu.
A blasted little —
Right.
Somebody in a little corner.
No question, I do feel it's psychological.
So can we be free of
the desire to be psychologically secure?
That's right.
That is the question.
Of course it is.
That's the nub of it.
Right.
I mean, last night we had
a talk, and I said —
And it was a very serious talk.
Yes.
It was a very serious talk.
It was the first time we had talked
to someone who had a very serious relationship
with a person who had had a very serious
relationship with a person who had been in a relationship
with a person who was
a person who was a man.
I was just sitting there and thinking about it.
I said, I've got to get out of this.
I've got to go and I've got
to go and I've got to go.
That's right. That is the question.
Of course it is. That's the nub of it.
Last night I was listening to some people about...
Madhuri, one of them was holding...
he was the chairman or what he was...
and they were all talking about Ireland, various things.
Each man was completely convinced...
That's right. I sit in on meetings every week.
Each man thinks his territory is the most important.
So we have given...
man has given more importance to psychological security...
than to biological, physical security.
Yes, but it's not clear why
he should delude himself in this way.
That is, he has deluded himself. Why?
The answer is there, why?
We've got two minutes more.
We'll have to stop at two.
Images, power...
No, sir, they are much
deeper. Why has he given importance?
He seems to think that... we, not he...
we seem to think that's
where security is, that's most important.
No, look more into it.
The me is the most important thing.
That's the same thing.
No, no. Me.
My position, my happiness, my
money, my house, my wife. Me.
But isn't it that each person feels
he is the essence of the whole?
The me is the very essence of the whole.
I would feel that if the me were gone...
the rest wouldn't mean anything.
That's the whole point.
The me is the essence of the whole.
The me gives me complete security, psychologically.
But it seems all-important.
Of course. All-important.
Yes, because if people say, if I am sad...
then the whole world has no meaning, right?
Well, it's not only that, but it's...
I am sad if the me is not important.
No, no, I don't...
We are saying the me...
in the me is the greatest security.
That's what we think.
No. Not we think it is so.
What do you mean it is so?
In the world, what is happening.
That is what is happening, but
it's a delusion which is happening.
We'll come to that later.
I think that's a good point.
That it is so that the me is...
I like that way of getting at it.
The me is what is important. That's all it is.
That's all. Psychologically.
Me, my country, me, my God, me, my...
It's very hard to let that in, you know.
It is two o'clock, we better start.
We at least got your voice.
Right.